We start בבא בתרא Bava Batra today, the last of the three
מסכתות Masechtot that make up סדר נזיקין, Seder Nezikin, but what used
to be מסכת נזיקין, Masechet Nezikin, 30 31 31 פרקים Perakim long
tractate, which is broken up into three sections of ten each. So
again to remind people, בבא בתרא Bava Batra just means the last
gate. There actually is a בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, בבא מציעא, Bava
Metzia, and בבא בתרא Bava Batra in כלים Kelim in טהרות, Taharos,
which also has 30 פרקים. Perakim. So you know, the גמרא Gemara
has a discussion whether to treat it all as one מסכת Masechet
or as three מסכתות, Masechtot, but it seems clear that initially it
was conceptualized as one very long מסכת Masechet with three parts. That
being said, you know, it's worth trying to think about, okay, how
do we sort of characterize these ten פרקים? Perakim? So in a
way, בבא קמא Bava Kamma and בבא בתרא Bava Batra have a
more clear identity than בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia. You know, maybe it's
the general story of a middle child. So anyway,
בבא קמא Bava Kamma was all about torts, right, about your animals
that damage, or property that damages, people that damage people, people damage
property, you know, theft, burglary. בבא בתרא Bava Batra mostly fits in
the section in the רמב"ם Rambam called קנין, Kinyan, things that have
to do with acquisition, although the opening פרקים Perakim have to do
with הלכות שכנים, Hilchos Shecheinim, laws governing neighbors. And we discussed this
last two days because really the last פרק Perek of בבא מציעא
Bava Metzia was a lead-in to this. What I can do in
my property and how much I have to be careful that things
I do in my property don't impact you, you know, in your
property and how much I would have to distance certain activities to
prevent them from damaging you and so on. Also the opening פרק,
Perek, that's really the second פרק Perek is about that. The opening
פרק, Perek, השותפין, HaShutafin, which we're about to see, is what happens
when we try to divide property between us. You know, some of
this was really already begun in the last פרק Perek of בבא
מציעא, Bava Metzia, how do we have to sort of how do
we divide the property? But within the context of how do we
divide the property, the first thing we're going to be looking at
in our משנה Mishnah is building a wall. Who was it, Robert
Frost, right, walls make good neighbors, was that it? Anyway, so the
idea of the first issue is not only the question of how
do we divide the property when we're dividing it, but do I
have a responsibility, do I have a responsibility to make sure that
I don't look into your property? And you know, we would call
that in contemporary terms a right of privacy. So those types of
issues, which is part of the more general הלכות שכנים, Hilchos Shecheinim,
you know, being somebody's neighbor and not causing direct or indirect types
of damage and so on. So that's really the opening two פרקים.
Perakim. Then we move on to the third פרק, Perek, which is
חזקת הבתים, Chazkat HaBatim, which is the one that's a very big
פרק Perek that's done classically in ישיבות, Yeshivos, which has to do
with, you know, the fact that if I am three years on
your property, I can claim that I purchased it from you even
if I don't have the documentation to prove it. Because I could
say it's sort of like with your tax returns, right, you don't
have to hold on, what, how many years are you supposed to
hold on, seven? Okay, so here three. You can assume if nobody
protested me being on their property for three years, I had a
right to say that I don't need to hold on to the
documentation any longer. So the evidence that I've been on it for
three years serves as evidence that I bought it. Now, if I
admit I didn't buy it and I'm saying that I was on
it three years, you didn't say anything, obviously that doesn't, not obviously,
people get that confused, that doesn't give me a right to the
land just because I was here for three years, but it can
serve as evidence to the fact that I bought it and I
don't have to produce documentation. So from there we start turning away
from neighbors into questions about rights, you know, claims of ownership and
so on. And from there we move on to a lot of
issues about ownership. So for example, the fourth פרק, Perek, fourth and
fifth and sixth פרק Perek are all about buying things. The fourth
פרק Perek is המוכר את הבית. HaMocher et HaBayit. When you sell
a house, and when you sell other things, what's considered implicitly included
in the sale? המוכר את הספינה, HaMocher et HaSefina, when you sell
a boat, is the fifth פרק, Perek, what's implicit in the sale?
Okay, the sixth פרק Perek is המוכר פירות, HaMocher Peirot, you're selling
fruit. Now it's not always what's implicit in the sale, there are
other issues as well, you know, honest weights and measures. If the
fruit goes bad, then who's to blame? Can I get my money
back if I buy wine and three days later it turns sour?
Right, so all these types of laws governing, you know, governing sort
of transactions and sales and purchases. So that's really what we start
dealing with is aspects of transactions. And then the last three
פרקים, Perakim, יש נוחלין, Yesh Nochalim, מי שמת, Mi she'meit, and גט
פשוט, Get Pashut, are about death and dying, which is also though
from the perspective of ownership and transfer of ownership. So it's about
who has a right to inherit, what is the sort
of order of inheritance, and about deathbed bequests and wills. Okay, so
there's a lot about, you know, the opening is about neighbors and
then it goes to aspects of buying and selling and then it
goes to transfer of property through death and through wills and so
on. So there is a pretty good coherence about them, pretty couple
of major themes. the themes. As I said, בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia,
which we just finished, is more of a mix, you know, בבא
מציעא Bava Metzia opens up with also like debates about who found
something, then it gets into there is sort of like this lost
objects but also this question of division, just to remind you, right?
The second פרק Perek is אלו מציאות, Elu Metziot, then there is
a lot about שומרים, Shomrim, there is a lot about lending money
and we ended, you know, about the question about charging ריבית, Ribit,
we ended with issues about taking collateral and so on. So there
are some like dominant themes there, but it does feel a little
bit more like a hodgepodge whereas here, you know, basically, unlike it's
a lot after the first two פרקים Perakim certainly, it's basically about
קניינים, Kinyanim, about sort of like selling and buying and transacting, you
know, and changing ownership and so on. All right, so that's sort
of in terms of the overarching theme about this, and just to
give you a little bit of a look forward, the next מסכת
Masechet is סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So if you want to think and then
מכות. Makkot. So if you want to think about it, like these
three מסכתות Masechtot or this thirty פרק Perek מסכת Masechet of נזיקין
Nezikin lays out the sort of the, you know, not secular law,
what's the word? Civil law, okay, the laws sort of engaging property
and interactions between people including about torts and property and so on,
and then we turn to the court system that's going to adjudicate
the law, and that's like מסכת סנהדרין Masechet Sanhedrin and so on.
All right, so that's sort of like, you know, how to think
about all of סדר נזיקין. Seder Nezikin. The other thing to know
is that there are not so many words per page here, and
that's for two reasons: number one is that there's a lot of
like what we would call like juicy thick סוגיות, Sugyot, you know,
with a lot of sort of discussion, so there are big תוספות,
Tosafot, but even besides the big תוספות, Tosafot, I mean you see
that even right at the beginning, like I don't know, I mean
just flip through the first few דפים, Dapim, you know, well okay,
there's a little אגדתא Aggadta in the first פרק, Perek, but if
you look at like ה עמוד ב, Hey Amud Bet, you see
a דף Daf that's almost all תוספות, Tosafot, but it really picks
up in the end of the second פרק. Perek. Why? Because at
the end of the second פרק, Perek, רש"י'ס Rashi's commentary stops and
we have the רשב"ם, Rashbam, who is רש"י'ס Rashi's grandson.
Now, actually it's pretty funny because, I'm sorry, not the end of
the second, the beginning of the third, my apologies, beginning of the
third פרק, Perek, because if you look at דף כט עמוד א,
Daf Kaf Tet Amud Aleph, it says עד כאן פירש רש"י זצ"ל,
Ad kan peirash Rashi zatzal, right in the middle of the
רש"י, Rashi, מכאן ואילך פירש רבינו שמואל בר מאיר, Mikan ve'eylakh peirash
Rabbeinu Shmuel bar Meir, the רשב"ם, Rashbam, which is רש"י'ס Rashi's grandson.
And if you look at the side, it's very funny 'cause the
side says בדפוס פיזרו, Bidfus Pizaro, in the original like in an
earlier printing, נדפס כאן מת רש"י. Nidpas kan met Rashi. רש"י Rashi
died here, like as he was writing he dropped dead right over
here. You know, this is about דף כט עמוד א Daf Kaf
Tet Amud Aleph where his... anyway, it doesn't mean literally, but it
means like... it's actually not true. It's not like he died in
the middle of writing his commentary to בבא בתרא. Bava Batra. I
should have looked it up but there's all this scholarship about רש"י'ס
Rashi's commentary to the גמרא, Gemara, and he wrote like I think
three editions of his commentary, which is why the רש"י Rashi on
the רי"ף, Rif, really some scholars believe because it's not always the
same as the רש"י Rashi on the גמרא, Gemara, was an earlier
edition of רש"י. Rashi. And I think that there's a question here,
not like that... I have to check. I'll check it before we
get to this, I'll look into it, but it has something to
do with like... and there's other מסכתות Masechtot he didn't write at
all. We have actually somebody who it says רש"י Rashi in quote
marks but really isn't רש"י, Rashi, it's the ריב"ן Rivan or somebody
else. But it seems that like here maybe he didn't write his
final edition to בבא בתרא. Bava Batra. Anyway, I don't know, but
it's not like he was... this was the last thing he was
working on when he died, okay, there's more to that story. But
anyway, but because רש"י, Rashi, we stop with רש"י Rashi and we
transition to the רשב"ם, Rashbam, also interesting like in פסחים Pesachim you
have both רש"י Rashi the last פרק Perek and the רשב"ם. Rashbam.
So the רשב"ם Rashbam is the sort of is two things: רשב"ם
Rashbam is both a commentator, like if you know read רשב"ם על
התורה, Rashbam al haTorah, he's even more terse than רש"י. Rashi. He's
a very פשט-oriented Pshat commentator, but in the context of the גמרא,
Gemara, he was the first of the generation of the בעלי התוספות,
Baalei haTosafot, okay? The רשב"ם Rashbam was, anybody know who's older... he
was whose younger brother? רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam was his younger brother,
okay? So and the... yeah exactly, so רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam was
like the clear like major force of the beginning of the תוספות'ס
Tosafot's activity, but the רשב"ם Rashbam was a part of that. And
the תוספות Tosafot activity is to not just say here's what this
line in the גמרא Gemara means and every now and then smooth
out a tiny little problem, but the תוספות Tosafot activity is to
constantly be comparing it to other סוגיות Sugyot and to work through
all of the problems that comes out when you look at it
as other סוגיות Sugyot and how do you make this fit with
this and fit with that and fit with that? So the רשב"ם
Rashbam is like a blending of רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, which
actually makes it quite difficult because what you want is you want
a simple פשט Pshat of the גמרא. Gemara. Let me get a
basic פשט Pshat and now let me problematize it and now maybe
I'll have to revise it. But you know, to sort of be
working through... I don't even get basic פשט Pshat yet until you're
introducing me to all these things, right, it just makes sort of
the... it makes for slower going, but what it does is it
also makes the דפים Dapim much shorter because basically every דף Daf
has two תוספות'ס Tosafot's on it, תוספות Tosafot and רשב"ם. Rashbam. So,
you know, the דפים Dapim are much smaller.
not just classic ראשונים, rishonim, even ראשונים rishonim who don't write, who
don't write on other מסכתות, masechtos, write on בבא בתרא. Bava Basra.
So it's a very, there's a lot of. That's why I just
personally, when, you know, when like talking about years in yeshiva, I
never really enjoyed בבא בתרא Bava Basra so much because, I mean
no, I don't mean to dis- whatever. You'll love it, okay? But
I found, but to me, I'm not talking about learning בקיאות, bekius,
I'm talking about learning בעיון. be-iyun. Because first of all, like, you
have to just get through so much before you can start about
thinking about like what do I think about this, right? There's just
so much on the page with רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafos and
so many ראשונים, rishonim, more ראשונים rishonim than on most other מסכתות,
masechtos, like, you know, to sort of do your due diligence before
you can think about any sort of anything that like, well, you
know, how would I work this out? It's like, there's just- it's
very weighted down. Also, another interesting challenge, and some people love it
because of this, but I also found it challenging, and I mentioned
this the other day,
was that almost nothing here can be linked to a פסוק pasuk
in the תורה. Torah. When you get to יש נוחלין, Yesh Nochalim,
yes, then you have the order of inheritance. But even there, יש
נוחלין Yesh Nochalim is immediately followed by this פרק perek about deathbed
bequests and wills, which basically sort of subverts the whole order of
inheritance. But okay, there you have it. You have a little bit
about the honest weights and measures, and that's going to sort of
come up in some aspects about מכירה. mechira. But you have the
huge מסכת maseches of which most of it is sort of like
חז"ל Chazal figuring out how to create laws of ordering in society,
not based on an interpretation of a תורה Torah מצוה, mitzvah, like
purely based on חז"ל. Chazal. So for some people, that's really exciting,
right? It shows sort of the power of חז"ל. Chazal. They created
all this תורה, Torah, you know, not just in an interpretive role.
And normally we often think of, oh well, if it's not interpreting
דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, it's a safeguard. This isn't a safeguard, this is like
substantive laws, okay, but not based on any particular פסוק. pasuk. But
I don't know, to me I like a lot more when it's
sort of in constant conversation with a פסוק pasuk or a מצוה
mitzvah of the תורה. Torah. So it's an interesting, again, from like
that perspective. The last thing I'll say and then we'll actually sort
of start reading it is, you know, about the question about like
how many pages- it's very few words per page, but it's like
the longest מסכת maseches in דפים, dapim, right? It goes to, you
know, what is it, קע"ו, Kuf-Ayin-Vav, 175 דף. daf. So there's a
story that they asked the וילנא גאון Vilna Gaon and they said
to him, which מסכת maseches has the most words? So if you
think about it, ברכות Berachos is like the opposite. ברכות Berachos is
huge amount of words, like very little תוספות, Tosafos, big דפים, dapim,
lots of אגדתא, agadata, you know, but not too- not as many
דפים. dapim. So anyway, so apparently the story is- and I don't
know, שבת Shabbos is like somewhere in the middle, right? It's very
long, but it's got- it's got, you know, but it has a
medium amount of words per page. Anyway, so the story is something
like that the וילנא גאון Vilna Gaon said, "Well, if you take
everything the way it's printed, then ברכות. Berachos. If you take all
the words I put in and the ב"ח Bach puts in, then
it's שבת. Shabbos. If you take the words I put in and
the ב"ח Bach puts out, it's בבא בתרא." Bava Basra. Anyway, it's
like through all the possible, you know, variations based on like what
your גרסאות girsaos would be. Now it'd be very easy to figure
out with a computer, I don't know if anybody has done it.
But anyway, so while it's certainly the most דפים, dapim, it is
questionable whether it is- it is questionable whether it's the longest מסכת
maseches in terms of words, which means that our actual דף יומי
daf yomi will not be as many words to cover and will
give us maybe more opportunity to explore a little more depth some
of the ideas. Okay, with that being said, let us now begin
בבא בתרא. Bava Basra. Okay, so
השותפים, hashutfim, now partners, okay, in a field, they jointly owned a
field, and then actually the word I should not say field because
we're going to see it's important חצר, chatzer, which means a yard,
so it means that they both have houses opening up into a
yard and they now want to split the- you know, they each
have their individual houses, they have a shared yard,
and now they want to split the yard. Okay, so שרצו לעשות
מחיצה בחצר, sheratzu la'asos mechitza be-chatzer,
they agree to put a wall separating it- what? A division. A
division, well, no, a wall, okay. The word, I mean the difference
between like how thick is it or whatever, all right, we'll see,
but anyway, it doesn't matter, a wall or a division, a wall
in the- between dividing their two yards, so maybe the- the yards
are already divided, you know, they each own their own private yard
but there's no wall between them, or maybe they're dividing their yards
and in the process of dividing the- of splitting the yard in
half they want to actually put a wall. It sounds like it's
the latter because if they already had the separate yards then they
wouldn't be שותפים, shutafim, they would just be שכנים, shcheinim, right? So
you've- you got that, right? They'd want to say שכנים שרצו לעשות
מחיצה. shcheinim sheratzu la'asos mechitza. So the point is presumably they have
a shared yard, they're agreeing to split the yard, and in the
process of splitting the yard they're agreeing to put a wall up
between the yard. Okay, so בונים את הכותל באמצע, bonim es hakosel
be-emtza, so they build a wall- here you see it switches from
מחיצה mechitza to כותל- kosel they build a wall in the middle.
Now obviously it's in the middle, well, you know, and what do
you mean in the middle? Like maybe the yard isn't divided one-third
and
two-thirds, maybe we have different- you know, different parts of the yards
were- what, maybe we just own different degrees of the yard. So
באמצע be-emtza does not mean down the middle of the yard. What
באמצע be-emtza means is the thickness of the wall takes up, you
know, is half in one- person's yard and half in the other
person's yard. So the line between the yards might not go straight
down the middle for various number of factors. But wherever that line
is, the wall half of its thickness is on one
person's yard and half of it is on the other person's yard.
Okay, בונים את הכותל באמצע. bonim et hakotel be'emtza. מקום שנהגו לבנות
גביל גזית כפיסים לבנים בונים. makom shenahagu livnot gvil gazis kfisim leveinim
bonim. We'll see, yes, let's keep on reading. מקום שנהגו לבנות גביל
גזית כפיסים לבנים בונים. makom shenahagu livnot gvil gazis kfisim leveinim bonim.
So whatever the standard way of building walls in yards was, then
without specifying otherwise, your deal is seen to be understood to be
shaped by the implicit norms of the community, of the society. So
if you agreed to build a wall and the standard was גביל,
gvil, גביל gvil is like stone which is not sort of smooth,
not sort of carved smoothly, then that would be the implicit agreement.
If it's גזית gazis which is hewn stone, like smoothed stone, that
would be the implicit agreement. כפיסים, kfisim, which is
whatever כפיסים kfisim are, some type of other type of, I think
it's like half bricks. Half bricks, right, כפיסים kfisim are half bricks.
לבנים leveinim are full bricks. Whatever the practice is, בונים. bonim. Now
this is relevant not just to say how much do I have
to invest in terms of the building materials, different building materials cost
more, but also if you remember this came up in the last
דף daf or second to last דף daf in בבא מציעא, Bava
Metzia, these different building materials are thicker or thinner. And this is
basically the order of thickness that they're listed in the משנה. Mishna.
So partly the point is how much of my yard do I
have to contribute for the footprint of the
wall. So maybe I'm willing to pay for materials, but I don't
want, I didn't expect it to take up three טפחים tfachim in
my yard. No, it's all determined by the standard unless you are
explicit otherwise, the norms of the community sort of shape it. Now,
okay, well that, right, so that would be an interesting question. What
happens if there is no standard?
Okay, now, גביל, gvil, now the משנה Mishna spells it out. גביל,
gvil, let's say it's this uncarved, unsmoothed stone, זה נותן ג' טפחים
וזה נותן ג' טפחים. ze noten gimmel tfachim veze noten gimmel tfachim.
That's six טפחים tfachim wide, so each one has to give three
טפחים tfachim of their yard.
וגזית זה נותן טפחיים ומחצה וזה נותן טפחיים ומחצה. vegazis ze noten
tfachaim vechetzve veze noten tfachaim vechetzve. Carved, like sort of smooth stone
is five טפחים, tfachim, so each one gives two and a half.
ובכפיסים, uvkfisim, which is the type of half bricks, which have plaster
in the middle so they're wider because or than the the whole
bricks because here there's plaster combining them in the middle, זה נותן
טפחיים וזה נותן טפחיים. ze noten tfachaim veze noten tfachaim. That's a
total of four טפחים, tfachim, each one gives two. ובלבנים, uvleveinim, whole
bricks, זה נותן טפח ומחצה וזה נותן טפח ומחצה. ze noten tfach
uchetzve veze noten tfach uchetzve. That's three טפחים, tfachim, each one gives
one and a half. Okay, now before we go on, there's just
an interesting little תוספות Tosafot here,
which is as long as you're going to say, well you know
what, I'll hold off תוספות. Tosafot. Let's read to the end of
the משנה. Mishna. Okay, now, לפיכך, lefikach, because we can assume
that because the normal rule is that when people divide each one
gives a portion of their yard, obviously it's possible we can make
other arrangements. You could say to me, Dov, I want to build
a wall, and I say, I'm not, I have no interest in
building a wall, and you say, look, let's make this deal, if
you agree to pay for half of the wall we can build
it all on my property. Okay, or something like that. So sure,
it's possible other things could happen. It's all based on the agreement
that they have. Okay, but because the standard is is that you
build it that each one
contributes an equal part of their yard, that's the standard unless you
stipulate otherwise. Therefore, here's a wall built up between our properties for
a hundred years, we don't know our grandparents built it, and we
don't know who owns the yard underneath, what was that division of
that of those of the footprint of it, but we can assume
that it was half mine and half yours because those, that is
the standard unless it's stipulated otherwise. Okay, and that's where the משנה
Mishna now continues.
לפיכך אם נפל הכותל המקום והאבנים של שניהם. lefikach im nafal hakotel
hamakom veha'avanim shel sheneihem. And so obviously it's not when you already
explicitly knew the first half of the משנה, Mishna, then you wouldn't
have to say it. It means any standard case where you don't
know what the history of the wall is between the people, you
can assume that it went by the standard rule, which is that
each one contributed equally to the building materials and they contributed equally
to the footprint to their portion of the yard. And therefore they
would divide it equally without any other knowledge. One minute.
Okay, וכן בגינה, vechen begina, similarly, that's about a yard, a yard
where it's like a yard to our home where we'll do semi-private
things in it, we might lie around and sunbathe or who knows
what we're going to do in our yards. Okay, that's relevant because
maybe I said that too soon, but it's going to be relevant
because the question about about looking into somebody's yard and somebody's right
to do sort of private activities or the presumption of privacy when
they're doing things in their yard. And there's a possible difference between
that and between something like my garden or between something like my
field. My field out with my wheat field, maybe I don't have
a presumption of privacy. Might my garden, my house I have the
highest right/presumption of privacy.
Hierarchy. Okay, so now it moves from one to the next.
וכן בגינה. v'chein b'gina.
Similarly, if you're dealing with a garden, like a vegetable garden, okay?
מקום שנהגו לגדור מחייבין אותו. makom shenahagu ligdor mechayivin oto.
A place where it's the custom to build a wall, you obligate.
So how do you read that? How do you parse that sentence?
So the way the גמרא Gemara is going to say, and it
seems very much that way from the next sentence in the משנה,
Mishnah, the way you parse the sentence is the following: if you
divide a garden, a garden is a place where people normally have
walls between their, you know, one garden and their neighbor's garden. And
therefore, if we divide a garden, you can obligate me to build
a wall. One neighbor wants to, the other doesn't, say you gotta
build it. The standard, again, unless we stipulate otherwise, but the standard
is you build walls between gardens. So therefore, it is a—what? No,
all the more in a חצר. chatzer. That's the וכן בגינה. v'chein
b'gina. Okay, similarly in a גינה, gina, it is a place where
the normal is—the norm is to build a wall and you can
obligate. I understand what's bothering Michael, I'll get back to it in
a minute. אבל בבקעה, aval b'bikah, if it's in like a valley,
which is basically like a wheat field or something like that, מקום
שנהגו שלא לגדור, makom shenahagu shelo ligdor, that's a place where normally
walls are not built between people's, you know, wheat fields. Obviously there's
some demarcating line so we know whose is whose property, but there's
no need for privacy in a wall. So in that case, אין
מחייבין אותו, ein mechayivin oto, if we're going to split it or
whatever, you cannot obligate me. Now, אלא, ela, now let's say you
want to build a wall and I don't, so okay, גזונטהייט. gezunte
heit.
If אלא אם רוצה כונס לתוך שלו ובונה. ela im rotzeh kones
l'toch shelo u'voneh. So fine, go ahead and build a wall in
your own property, use it—you spend, you pay all the money for
the expenses, you put it all on your land. Be my guest,
I just don't want to contribute to it and I don't want
to contribute money and I don't want to contribute my land. So
you're—you're welcome to do that. ובונה
ועושה—now u'voneh v'oseh here's the question, because what did the משנה Mishnah
tell us above? It told us that if we have no idea
of the history of a wall, we're going to presume that both
people have rights—equally own the wall and equally own the property below.
So if you have a special case where you've built the wall
all of your own money and on your own property, what are
we going to do to remember 20 years from now, 100 years
from now, that it's your wall and not mine and that it's
on your property and it's not half on my property? So the
משנה Mishnah tells us the following: ועושה חזית מבחוץ. v'oseh chazis mibachutz.
You make some type of a חזית, chazis, like a some type
of a sign, some type of a, you know, marker on the
outside of the wall so that it'll remember—so that it'll be a
sign that you fully own the wall. Now the question, of course,
is: wait a minute, where's this marker? Like if it's on my
side of the wall, what's to stop me from removing it? If
it's on your side of the wall, what's to stop you from
building it like, you know, unjustly, you know, you know, let's say
we built a wall smack in the middle, okay? What I'm going
to do is I'm going to go ahead and make a חזית
chazis on my side of the wall that you won't see, so
that when the wall falls I'll claim it's all mine.
No, no, it's on the outside.
Wait, what is the outside? Your side—who—if this guy's—your side, oh no,
here we go. Okay,
here's ראובן's Reuven field, right? Here's שמעון's, Shimon okay? שמעון Shimon didn't
want to build a wall, so the whole wall was built on
ראובן's—on Reuven ראובן's Reuven side, right? Where's the חזית? chazis?
On
שמעון's Shimon side.
Okay, you put your חזית chazis here, what's to stop me from
coming and knocking it down?
No, but what's—to my mind, what he means is ראובן's Reuven side
will be nice and polished and שמעון's Shimon side will be a
little rough.
Oh, you mean so if I knock it down, you'll sort of
see there'll be—there'll be some evidence that I knocked it down.
Yeah, the other way around.
By the way, the—by the way, the contemporary law here is the
opposite. I put up a fence between me and my neighbor, the
nice side has to be facing the neighbor.
Ah, and that's how you know
whose side—and the inside, like where you see the structure of the
fence, is in my
back—well, whatever it is you do, you make it a little bit
structurally different.
I understand. Anyway, we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. You have to
make it in a way that's going to ensure that it can't
be made illegally, as it were, and that when it's going to
be made, it will be able to be preserved. Okay, so we'll
see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so when the—when we're—let's
finish. ועושה חזית מבחוץ, v'oseh chazis mibachutz, you make it on the
outside. לפיכך אם נפלה הכותל המקום והאבנים שלו. l'fichach im nafla hakosel
hamakom v'ha'avanim shelo. Therefore, if the wall falls down, because you have
this חזית, chazis, it's evidence that it's all your wall, so you
get to keep the whole wall and the—and the space underneath. אם
עשו מדעת שניהם, im asu mada'at sheneihem, now let's say they both
agreed to build it, okay? בונים את הכותל באמצע, bonim es hakosel
b'emtza, now this is in a place like a valley, a wheat
field where normally nobody would build a wall. And all of a
sudden these people decided. So here, what do you do? Then you
build it in the middle, okay? If they both agree, okay? באמצע
ועושים חזית מכאן ומכאן, b'emtza v'osim chazis mikan u'mikan, and you put
a חזית chazis on both sides. Now the question's why do you
need a חזית chazis at all, right? I mean, it is true
that a wall—what?
Then you—then on one side you'll put the חזית. chazis.
No, but you don't need—in the—in the first cases, you don't need
a חזית chazis
because there's a—there's a standard.
Right. So that's—so that's exactly it. Meaning in the valley, nobody ever
built walls. anyway, so you don't have any standard, but it still
raises the question, why don't you just say that no חזית chazis
means it's equal anyway? It is a question why you need two
חזיתs chazis rather than none. But that's what the משנה mishna says.
Here's a place where there's no standard, so where there's no standard
you use the חזית chazis as evidence to who owns the wall.
So either you have a חזית chazis on one side or you
have חזית chazis on both sides. Okay, לפיכך אם נפל הכותל המקום
והאבנים של שניהם. lefichach im nafal hakoseil hamakom veha'avanim shel sheneihem. It
falls down and they equally own it. So we'll worry about the
end later, right, why where is the חזית chazis and why do
you need two rather than zero? Shh. But, okay, but I want
to just go back to something that was implicitly bothering Michael, which
is really going to be what bothers the גמרא. gemara. One second.
Which is when you get to the גינה, gina, it sounds like
the dynamics in the גינה gina is the following: normal people have
walls between their gardens. Therefore, if we agree to split a garden,
I can force you to build a wall. So it sounds like
I can force you to build a wall even if you're not
interested in it. Whereas the opening part of the משנה mishna sounds,
if we agree to build a wall between our yards, here's how
it has to be built. Which gets to the core question which
is going to focus the גמרא gemara on, which is, can you
force somebody to build a wall if they don't want to? And
the reason for that is the core issue of the beginning of
the גמרא, gemara, which is, we would call it the right to
privacy, the גמרא gemara calls it היזק ראיה. hezek re'iyah. Is when
I'm able to look into a space which you would normally do
private or semi-private activities, is that considered like I'm damaging you? Okay,
and therefore if so, can you force a person to participate in
the building of a wall? So there's an inherent ambiguity in the
משנה. mishna. When it gets to the case of the גינה, gina,
it says you it's the standard is to build a wall, therefore
you can force a person. So then why isn't that true by
a חצר? chatzer? If the גמרא gemara assumes that there's certainly more
of a standard of walls between the חצרות? chatzeros? So why does
the opening part of the משנה mishna sound like we have to
agree to build a wall, you can't force the person? So that's
going to be the opening focus of the גמרא. gemara. Yes.
I just want to note, you know, maybe modern Hebrew is not
relevant at all, but חזית chazis and עורף oref are two terms.
חזית chazis means the front. Uh-huh.
חזית chazis from to like to see. Uh-huh.
חזית chazis just like in military terms, like campaign, when your soldiers
go to the front. That's called the חזית. chazis. Interesting.
And then חזית chazis from to see.
Yeah, exactly. So. And עורף oref in that in those in that
language is the back part.
It's not like...
Okay, so I want to say one more thing before we continue.
All right, we'll worry about חזית chazis later. I want to say
one more thing before we continue into the גמרא, gemara, which is
the משנה mishna gave, shh, the משנה mishna gave a whole list
of different types of building materials after a generic statement of הכל
כמנהג המדינה. hakol keminhag hamedina. Right. It's shaped by the norms and
then it gave you a whole list of what the different types
of possibilities are. So תוספות tosafos asks a very reasonable question: why
if say it's all shaped by the norms, just end there? Why
do you have to tell me, oh, it's this and it's this,
and it's this, and it's this, like whatever the norm is,
that's what the norm is. Now Michael asks a good question: what
if you don't know what the norm is? But the משנה mishna
didn't answer that either, right? The משנה mishna was just concretizing the
sense of הכל כמנהג המדינה. hakol keminhag hamedina. Why do I need
it to give a whole list of specific examples? So תוספות tosafos
says, what if the practice was to build with like גזית, gazis,
but actually the practice was to build with גזית gazis which was
like five טפחים tefachim here, but to use very big גזית gazis
of eight טפחים? tefachim? Okay, and he says the point of giving
these numbers was to actually say it's not always, it's not like
מנהג minhag always rules. מנהג minhag to some degree is balanced with
some sense of reasonable norms,
or not reasonable like objective types of criteria. So therefore, הכל כמנהג
המדינה, hakol keminhag hamedina, but גזית gazis would not you could not
demand more than X amount of width of גזית. gazis. You could
not demand more than X amount of גוויל. gevil. And that leads
רבינו תם, rabbeinu tam, if you look at
the
end of this תוספות tosafos בגוויל, begevil, he says,
the last narrow line of that תוספות tosafos בגוויל, begevil, like of
the, you know, of where the תוספות tosafos is the most narrow,
ונראה לרבינו תם דדווקא בהוצא ודפנא, venira lerabbeinu tam dedavka behutza vedafna,
that when you can go down you can go down to like
הוצא ודפנא, hutza vedafna, that's some type of like planks or whatever,
very thin division. אבל פחות מכאן, aval pachos mikan, if they there
was some מנהג minhag to do even a thinner division or a
weaker division, so that's below a certain minimum. So פחות מכאן אפילו
נהגו מנהג הדיוט הוא. pachos mikan afilu nahagu minhag hedyot hu.
Even if the מנהג minhag even if that was the מנהג, minhag,
it's not a legitimate מנהג. minhag. Okay, it's a מנהג הדיוט minhag
hedyot is a nicer way of saying מנהג שטות. minhag shtus. Okay.
What?
Isn't it nicer?
הדיוט? hedyot? Yeah, it's better to call somebody a הדיוט hedyot than
to call them a שוטה. shoteh. Anyway, ומוכח מכאן דיש. umuchach mikan
deyesh. מנהגים שאין לסמוך עליהם אפילו היכא דתנן הכל כמנהג המדינה. minhagim
she'ein lismoch aleihem, afilu heicha ditnan akol k'minhag hamedina. You can't trust
all מנהגים. minhagim. Now I want to just say one thing about
this right now and obviously we'll get to it more, but there's
a big difference when we talk about issues of מנהג. minhag. First
of all, okay, there's like חיים סולובייצ'יק, Haym Soloveitchik,
the current חיים סולובייצ'יק, Haym Soloveitchik, רב יוסף דב סולובייצ'יק Rav Yosef
Dov Soloveitchik's son, דוקטור חיים סולובייצ'יק, Dr. Haym Soloveitchik, you know, he
made a good point many years ago when I was in a
class of his about the difference in modern Hebrew between the word
מנהג minhag and נוהג. nohag. Okay, מנהג minhag means custom, נוהג nohag
means practice. In traditional Hebrew you don't have that difference. Okay, it's
not a custom, we could have a custom to do כפרות, kapparos,
we could have a custom to eat מילכיגס milchigs on שבועות, Shavuos,
okay, but we have a נוהג, nohag, we have a practice of
how do we build walls. It's not like it's a custom, okay,
it's how do we how do we normally go about doing these
types of things, right? So normal anyway that's just one issue, but
the other issue is there's a big difference between so you know
when between going by by
practices in in sort of monetary matters, right? We're agreeing to build
a wall, we assume that without being spec- saying otherwise, we to
agree to any type of agreement, we assume it's governed by the
norms that these things are normally done by unless we unless we
articulate otherwise. That becomes almost implicit in our contact in our agreement
shaped by the standard types of norms. That's very different than saying
you know like I said I have a מנהג minhag to שלוג
כפרות shlog kapparos on ערב יום כיפור. Erev Yom Kippur. Okay, that
sort of creates some new type of a practice which somehow obligates
me or my descendants or my community because we all have this
practice to maintain it and sustain it. When we normally talk about
מנהגים, minhagim, we normally think about customs. הכל כמנהג המדינה akol k'minhag
hamedina is something very different. It's norms of society and of business
and of transactions whatever implicitly governing the arrangement. But when you so
when רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam wants to say there's some types of
מנהג הדיוט minhag hedyot that we throw out, you know my sense
is here because רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam was famously said מנהג minhag
is דאותיות d'otiyos גיהנום. gehennom. Okay, so anyway
so you know the point seems to be that he has like
a like there are two agendas here: one is to say that
even in monetary matters מנהג minhag can't totally govern, there has to
be some types of limits and parameters, but also סתם stam what
we would normally call מנהגים, minhagim, סתם stam customs, you can't like
let מנהגים minhagim get out of control. Sometimes they don't make any
sense, sometimes they're actually contradictory to other תורה Torah values, to other
הלכות halachos and so on. So it's an interesting point about if
you want to think about it of like a dynamic of like
you know the and the you know the laypeople and the rabbinic
authorities like you know how people are practicing but but we as
you know either the legal heads or the religious heads sort of
feel have to put some parameter objective parameters on that at the
same time in some type of a dynamic. So I just want
to say that that was interesting the both the balance of הכל
כמנהג המדינה akol k'minhag hamedina with saying and here would be the
numbers. So which is it: the מנהג המדינה minhag hamedina or is
it the numbers? And there's some type of way that they work
in conjunction, yes. Or in tension.
Can I pick up on the way you read the משנה? mishna?
You read taking this an example of מנהג המדינה minhag hamedina מקום
שנהגו לגדור מחבירו, makom shenahagu lidor me'chaviro,
which you could have potentially taken it to mean if it's a
מקום שנהגו. makom shenahagu. I understand. But you took it to mean
that since it is a מקום...
makom... Which is how the גמרא Gemara correct. Correct. So it's not
exactly...
I understand but that's how the גמרא Gemara reads it and I
think that's פשט pshat because that's the difference between גינה gina and
ביקעה. bika. Let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, סברוה מאי מחיצה
גודא. savruah mai mechitza guda.
So we assumed that when it said when they agreed to make
a מחיצה mechitza it mean they agreed to make what's a מחיצה
mechitza a wall. Okay now here we don't mean wall versus divider.
We mean whatever a wall is, divider you know stone, brick, you
know barbed wire doesn't matter. Okay, it means a division. Okay, so
they agreed to make a division and only because they agreed to
make a division, not a division, I'm going to say a wall,
only because they agreed to make a wall that's why a wall
has to be put up.
Okay, דתניא ditanya like we saw in a ברייתא braisa that מחיצה
mechitza means... See in contemporary experience you don't have to tell people
that a מחיצה mechitza means a means a divider okay or means
a wall. But מחיצה mechitza is not used so commonly that word
in rabbinic literature. So therefore we're going to bring a proof that
the word מחיצה mechitza is a noun and it refers to a
physical object and it refers to a wall.
Okay, all over מסכת סוכה Masechet Sukkah it says so interesting.
All over the מסכת. masechet. מחיצה? mechitza? Yeah. מחיצה? mechitza? It's like
for the דפנות. defanos.
It's not a vocabulary word of מסכת סוכה Masechet Sukkah okay I
don't want
to interrupt. Immediate impression. Not walls?
It's oh so מחיצה גבוהה עשרה. mechitza gevoha asara. Yeah.
Yeah. That's a good point. I mean it's it's strange that no
I don't know I'll have to take a look. No מחיצה mechitza
of סוכה sukkah means okay I'll have to take a look. I
don't remember offhand maybe you're right whether it's מחיצה mechitza or wall.
Okay anyway or you know כותל. kotel. דפנות. defanos. דפנות. defanos. Thank
you. דפנות defanos is the common word in סוכה, sukkah, not מחיצה.
mechitza. We'll take a look. Alright anyway it's interesting because it runs
to a ברייתא. braisa. So somebody can afterwards go take a go
use בר אילן Bar Ilan and do a look for מחיצה mechitza
in tannaitic literature. דתניא מחיצת הכרם שנפרצה. ditanya mechitzat hakerem shenifretza. You
have a wall between a vineyard and a... Let's say a wheat
field, okay, that fell down, okay, or a or a tree, you
know, or an orchard. You have I'm sorry, no, it's a wheat
field, excuse me. It's a wheat field. Okay, so one minute let's
just check רש"י Rashi here.
Yeah, a wheat field. You have a wall between a vineyard and
a wheat field. אומר לו גדור. Omer lo gdor. Now of course
that wall prevents כלאים kilayim concerns because if you have vines growing
right near wheat, it creates כלאים. kilayim. But if there's a wall
between them, then they can be right next to each other physically
proximate as long as the physical wall divides them. If there's no
wall they need a certain amount of distance, but if there is
a wall they can both be right up against the wall. So
מחיצת הכרם שנפרצה. Mechitzas hakerem shenifreza. Now that wall broke open and
now the wheat and the vines are creating כלאים. kilayim. But there's
an interesting הלכה halacha of כלאים kilayim that if you're trying to
prevent it, if you're trying if you're intending to build a wall,
even though physically they're right next to each other it's not yet
כלאים kilayim because the פסוק pasuk says לא תזרע כרמך כלאים. Lo
tizra kormacho kilayim. It has to be like you planted it, like
you wanted it. So if you're actually working to build the wall,
as long as you're sort of intending to do that, it doesn't
yet become כלאים. kilayim. So אומר לו גדור. Omer lo gdor. So
you say to the guy who owns the vineyard, build up that
wall. Now there's an interesting הלכה halacha in כלאים kilayim that the
guy who owns the vineyard is considered to be the the one
who is damaging the wheat field and not vice versa, although both
would become כלאים. kilayim. And the reason for that is is the
way תוספות Tosfos explains is that the distance between the the the
vines,
the grape vines and the wheat have to be four אמות amos
because that is the space you need to maneuver when you are
tending to vines. So therefore it is defined, the need for the
space is is because of the vines. That conceptually if you have
vines, you know, the next you know because of the way you
maneuver around the vines, you know, something to be separate from them
has to be four אמות amos away. So because that distance is
required because of the realities of tending to vines, the vines are
the ones that are seen as encroaching. Okay, so we're not going
to worry about that right now, that's a כלאים kilayim issue, but
nevertheless it's the responsibility of the guy who owns the vineyard. He
is seen as the מזיק. mazik. So his responsibility to build the
fence. So אומר לו גדור, Omer lo gdor, you say build up
the wall. חוזר ונפרצה, Chazar venifreza, then it fell back again. אומר
לו גדור, Omer lo gdor, and you say build it. And this
time already he says to heck with it. נתייאש ממנו ולא גדר,
Nisyashesh mimenu velo gador, he decides to heck with it, I'm not
going to bother. In that case, הרי זה קידש. harei ze kideish.
As soon as he gives he decides he's not going to bother,
it it makes everything כלאים. kilayim. The phrase is פן תקדש המלאה,
pen tikdash hamlaya, so it's sort of drawing on the on the
פסוק. pasuk. הרי זה קידש, Harei ze kideish, okay, that's not our
issue. וחייב באחריותה. Vechayav beachrayusa. And because he was negligent, he has
to pay the owner of the wheat field for trashing up all
of his wheat. Now תוספות Tosfos asks an interesting question, why isn't
it היזק שאינו ניכר? hezek she'eino nikkar? You know, what defines ניכר?
nikkar? Okay, so anyway we won't focus on that just yet. If
we have a minute we could get back to that, but let's
keep on moving.
The point being that מחיצה mechitzah means a wall. טעמא דרצה. Ta'ama
deratza. So basically that's how we read the משנה. Mishnah. So the
משנה Mishnah is if you agree to build a wall, you have
to build a wall, which means I can't compel you to build
a wall. That is the key question here: can I compel you
to build a wall? So טעמא דרצה, ta'ama deratza, so the reason
you have to build a wall is because you agreed to it.
הא לא רצה אין מחייבין אותו. Ha lo ratza ein mechayvin oso.
If you didn't, then you don't obligate it. אלמא, Alma, you see
from this,
היזק ראייה לאו שמיה היזק. hezek re'iah lav shemei hezek. Damage through
sight is not a היזק. hezek. Now I want to make this
clear, I want to just say two things about this sight. First
of all, this is not what the גמרא Gemara is going to
get to later, this metaphysical or superstitious, depending on where you're coming
from, idea of of עין הרע, ayin hara, okay? That I because
I look at your wheat or whatever, I look at your you
know your nice yard, I'm going to give it an עין הרע
ayin hara and all the grass is going to turn brown. Okay,
that is some idea that does come up, but that's not the
real point here. Forget any metaphysics. The point here is what we
would call a right to privacy. Do I feel that the fact
that you are looking to be seeing what I am doing, even
if what I'm doing is totally innocent, do I have a right
to not be observed by other people? Okay, now notice how I
framed it as, and this is a point I made I've discussed
a few weeks ago in when we were doing the end of
בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, in Western terms, right to privacy. You're encroaching
on my right, okay?
You know, הלכה halacha does not I'm not saying it never talks
about rights, but it more talks about obligations to other people, how
I can't act against somebody, you know, I can't hurt, what I
must do to somebody. And here too, the phrasing is: if I
am observing somebody else in their private domain, is it considered like
I am causing them injury? Okay, so that's as you could you
can say it's just another way of saying it, but it is
conceptually different. Okay, one way it's conceptually different is you could say
could I collect damages because you injured me? Now again, it's my
just because you say it's injury doesn't mean it's injury that you
could actually get paid for.
It's היזק שאינו. hezek she'eino. You know, it's not the type of
physical property damage. But the point is it puts it in a
different conceptual category. What we would call right to privacy, this is
calling it are you hurting somebody, damaging somebody in some way by
observing them in a place where they could think that they could
have a right to act in their own yard, in their own
space, in a way that's unobserved. So if the point is it
is considered like you're damaging somebody, then I can say, I can
demand that you participate in this wall, because you have an obligation
not to cause me damage through observing me in my yard. Right?
So that becomes, you know, that issue. Now again, because we're framing
it in terms of היזק, Hezek, you might remember that we had
a discussion, which is a בבא בתרא Bava Batra discussion that we
introduced at the end of בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, whether המזיק להרחיק
את עצמו ha-mazik le-har'chik et atzmo or הניזק להרחיק את עצמו. ha-nizak
le-har'chik et atzmo. Right? Who has the responsibility to keep away from
the damage? So because we're not calling it a right to privacy,
we're calling it a damage, so I go there and I say
to David, "David, you have to participate in this wall. I don't
want you to damage me, to do this damage to me of
observing me." So you could say, "It's your responsibility to prevent yourself
from being damaged. Go build a wall in your own domain." So
that's not what we're assuming here, but I just want to emphasize
this is what happens when you call, when it really determines, is
significant how we frame the discourse. We're not calling this right to
privacy, we're calling this היזק. Hezek. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara here
is assuming though, if it is היזק, Hezek, then that means you're
the, you would be a potential מזיק, Mazik, so you have to
be,
you
are responsible to prevent that. So therefore you have to contribute to
the wall and to, you know, to the space and the cost
of the wall. Okay, so if we were there first? What? Well,
if the משנה, Mishna, that's an interesting question which we'll get to,
like if somebody was operating in a certain way and then somebody
moved in or whatever, okay, we'll definitely get to that. But here
we're having, we both had yards and now we both agree to
split it, so we were all at the same time. So therefore
the question in the משנה, Mishna, can you force somebody to build
a wall or is it only if they agree to build a
wall, is a deep question of is היזק ראיה שמי היזק. Hezek
Re'iah shemei Hezek. Okay. So the way to read the משנה Mishna
that you only have to build the wall when we agree to
it means fundamentally you can't force me. Fundamentally, if I am looking
into you doing private things in your yard or, you know, I
am not considered to be damaging you, or if my, the fact
that I have the ability to look in your yard will restrain
you from doing certain things, that is not a legitimate complaint you
have against me. And if you want to deal with that, you
build your own wall. You can't demand that I participate in the
wall.
Just, just because I'm trying to understand, because we said, okay, we
got to divide this, then it's a wall or could we say
we want to build a wall, then okay how thick the wall?
That's meaning if we just decided, get what I'm saying? Like the
way we were saying the מחיצה Mechitza is a גודא, guda, it's
a wall.
I mean, I would have thought. That's what the משנה Mishna says,
הכל כמנהג המדינה. hacol ke-minhag ha-medina. I would have thought it just.
My other question is if it's a ראיה, re'iah, then it's interesting
how they're talking about how wide it is instead of how high
it is, which you'd think that the.
Those are unrelated points. Meaning the,
your need to participate, what you're saying is I don't know, let's
say there was, you know,
whatever the reason, there are many reasons why we build a wall,
my ability and, and there's, whatever there are standards in the community
of how, how high they are and how thick they are and
whatever, okay,
so once you have to build it you have to go by
those standards. What you're saying is let's say there's some, there's some
lack of matching up, let's say we normally build walls out of
I don't know, I don't want to get into that right now.
Okay, let's just bracket that. I understand what you're asking, but I'm
going to bracket that. Okay, so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
One more clarification,
I still don't get how we got from a ברייתא braita that's
dealing with כלאים kilayim which is economic damage.
No, that all that was to do was to show that the
word מחיצה mechitza meant wall. Now the question is what else could
the word מחיצה mechitza mean? So we're about to see. Okay, let's
hold off the questions, okay, we have ten minutes left to hold
off the questions. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
ואימא מחיצה פלוגתא. Ve'eima mechitza pelugta. So now you're going to see
the alternative. So a simple way of course that we read the
משנה Mishna is we agreed to build a wall, which means you
can't force the other person to build a wall. So the גמרא
Gemara said but let's say מחיצה mechitza means how do you know
מחיצה mechitza means a wall? Maybe מחיצה mechitza means a division. Maybe
it means once we agreed to divide, then you can force the
guy to build a wall. כדכתיב ותהי מחצת העדה. ke-dichtiv vat'hi mechtzat
ha-edah. מחצת העדה. mechtzat ha-edah. Thank you. So the division of the,
of the community when they came back with the spoils of war.
So the way to read the משנה Mishna would be השותפין שרצו
לעשות מחיצה, ha-shutfin she-ratzu la'asot mechitza, the
השותפין shutfin who agreed to divide the property, then they're forced to
participate in the wall. Okay? So which is sort of how the
end of the משנה Mishna reads by גינה. gina. Okay? But וכיון
דרצו, ve-kivan de-ratzu, as soon as they agreed, בונין את הכותל על
כרחו, bonin et ha-kotel al korcho, you can force the guy to
participate. אלמא היזק ראיה שמי היזק. alma Hezek Re'iah shemei Hezek. So
you see that actually it is considered a damage. So two very
important different ways of reading the משנה. Mishna. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, אי הכי האי שרצו לעשות מחיצה, i hachi hai she-ratzu
la'asot mechitza, when it said they want to make a מחיצה mechitza
which makes the word מחיצה mechitza a noun. שרצו לחצות מיבעי ליה
sheratzu lachatzot mibei lei or if you've used it as a verb,
they wanted to divide. הא גמרא gemara says אלא מאי גודא ela
mai guda so you want to say it means they wanted to
make a wall, בונין את הכותל bonin et hakotel why does it
say they built the כותל? kotel? That sounds like the noun, the
object is the כותל. kotel. בונין אותו מיבעי ליה bonin oto mibei
lei it should've said they built it, the מחיצה. mechitza. Why did
it switch from מחיצה mechitza to כותל? kotel? So the fact that
it switched makes it sound like maybe מחיצה mechitza isn't the object.
Maybe מחיצה mechitza is a division, a conceptual division. גמרא gemara says
no, אי תנא אותו ei tana oto had it said you build
it, the
מחיצה, mechitza, הוה אמינא במסיפס בעלמא. hava amina b'mispis b'alma. מסיפס mispis
רש"י Rashi says is
basically small little pegs that serve as a dividing line but do
not actually serve as a wall. They're a marker to show where
where the line of our property is. Okay? So therefore we wanted
to move to the word כותל kotel in order to emphasize that
it has to be a even if when we agree to make
some divider it's it's a real wall, it's a real divide. Okay?
אי תנא אותו הוה אמינא במסיפס בעלמא קא משמע לן כותל. ei
tana oto hava amina b'mispis b'alma kamashma lan kotel. Anyway, but our
read of the משנה mishnah which is certainly the פשט pshat of
the word מחיצה mechitza is that you only build the wall if
you agree to it. You can't be forced to, which means היזק
ראייה לאו שמיה היזק. hezek re-iyah lav shmeih hezek. So let's continue.
בונין את הכותל באמצע. bonin et hakotel b'emtza. פשיטא, pshita, of course
you build it in the middle. If they both agreed to build
it, of course you build it in the middle. גמרא gemara says
no, לא צריכא דקדים חד ורציה לחבריה. lo tzricha d'kadim chad v'ratzei
l'chavreih. And now this really works in the context that you were
agreeing to build the wall, not just agreeing to divide. I went
ahead and I said, David come on, please, we really need to
build this wall, it's really important to me. No, I don't want
to. Anyway finally after a month I got him to agree to
build it, okay? But I was the initiator and I was the
persuader. So in that case מהו דתימא mahu d'teima I might think
מצי אמר ליה matzi amar lei David could say to me, no,
כי איתרצאי לך באווירא ki itratzai lach b'avira I agreed to build
like in terms of the airspace that it would cut into the
air and maybe I agreed to pay for the building expense, but
בתשמישתא לא איתרצאי לך b'tashmishta lo itratzai lach
I didn't agree to give up some of the use of my
field so I was assuming it was all going to be in
your field, okay? It was all going to be in your yard.
So קא משמע לן kamashma lan that you can't say that. The
whole point of the משנה mishnah is once you agree, without stipulating
otherwise, it's assumed to be everything is down the middle. Fine. That's
פשט pshat in the משנה. mishnah. So now we've read the משנה,
mishnah, we agreed not to divide, we agreed to the wall, and
then the you cannot make any claims that you did not fully
take your half of the responsibility. It's assumed everything is down the
middle. And the point though being היזק ראייה לאו שמיה היזק hezek
re-iyah lav shmeih hezek that if you didn't agree to the wall
you can't be forced to build it. And now we're going ahead
and analyze this. Okay? והיזק ראייה לאו שמיה היזק? v'hezek re-iyah lav
shmeih hezek? Do you really mean to tell me היזק ראייה hezek
re-iyah is not considered a damage? תא שמע וכן בגינה. ta shema
v'chen b'gina.
Okay? Here it same similar by a גינה gina and it seems
like the way we're reading it is a גינה gina because it
is the norm to have a wall, you can force the guy
to build it. Right? As the משנה mishnah says you can force
the guy to build it. So that sounds like היזק ראייה שמיה
היזק. hezek re-iyah shmeih hezek. גינה שאני? gina shani? No, as a
גינה gina actually maybe you have more of a right to demand
a wall than a yard. Why is that? Okay? And now we
get כי דרבי אבא דאמר רבי אבא אמר רב הונא אמר רב
ki d'Rabbi Abba d'amar Rabbi Abba amar Rav Huna amar Rav אסור
לאדם לעמוד בשדה חברו בשעה שהיא עומדת בקמותיה. assur l'adam la-amod bisdeh
chaveiro b'sha-ah she-hi omedet b'kamoteha. You can't stand around being in your
friend's wheat field and gazing at it while it's there and it's
all like standing high and tall wheat and maybe you're appreciating it.
Why? Because of your that this now is the עין הרע. ayin
hara. Okay? You give it an עין הרע ayin hara and you
cause the wheat to get damaged. So the point is that you
may be in your yard, which is you know where you normally
think you have what I'll call again a right to privacy, you
have more rights to be you know for a wall than for
the garden. But גמרא gemara says no, maybe you could read the
משנה mishnah that in garden in particular I can demand you build
the wall so you don't that's a real damage. Your looking at
my vegetables will give them an עין הרע ayin hara and will
cause them to rot, okay, or something like that. So that's a
real damage. There I can demand it. But your some just looking
at me reading a book in my in my easy in my
like lounge chair you know in my yard, that's not a real
היזק hezek and that I can't demand. Okay? Which is a pretty
funny idea. A, it's funny because we don't really, I mean speak
for myself, believe in עין הרע, ayin hara, okay? But it's anyway,
but to think that that even if you do believe in עין
הרע ayin hara that there's more of an עין הרע ayin hara
around your vegetable garden than concerns about yourself.
But the person's eyeing it and saying he has all this ברכה
bracha I don't have this ברכה.
bracha. Right, I understand people are more jealous about people's wealth and
so on. Right? So that's the assumption of the גמרא. gemara.
Why you go עין הרע, ayin hara, if it's not about potential
real damage?
Well that's in the case of the גינה? gina? No, no, it's
the גמרא gemara understands I mean the assumption is it's עין הרע,
ayin hara, yeah, that's the issue. Okay? תוספות Tosafot asks then why
should then you should have to be able to build a wall
in a in your wheat field? But he says no, people aren't
around in the wheat field as much you know. So you have
so there you can't force a wall. But in a garden where
people are around and they'll be looking at it and it's an
עין הרע ayin hara concern, maybe that's the one case that you
can force a wall. Okay? So we're trying to make גינה gina
an exception. So let's keep on going. So the גמרא gemara says
like this. אה... ah...
okay...
והא v'ha this discussion is is why if we already
say that this
They shouldn't hang around, but
no, it's אסור assur for you to be looking at somebody's wheat,
but you can't force somebody to build a wall because people aren't
hanging because I'm not commonly in my wheat field the same way
I'm regularly in my neighboring garden. Okay. והכין קתני, V'hachin ktani, but
one minute, it says והכין V'hachin which sounds like it's the same
point as the beginning of the משנה. mishna. So it sounds like
the basic point is that you can force somebody to build a
wall in a חצר. chatzer. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אבני
גזית. Avnei Gazis. That means that once you're building the wall it
has to follow the building materials and the norms, that's the והכין,
V'hachin, but not the issue of whether you can force it or
not. Maybe you can only force it in a גינה, gina, you
can't force it in a חצר. chatzer. תא שמע, Tashma, no questions.
I'm not answering. תא שמע, Tashma, כותל חצר שנפל מחייבין אותו לבנות
עד ארבע אמות. Kosel chatzer shenafal mechayvin oso livnos ad arba amos.
There we have a next משנה mishna says that if the wall
of a חצר chatzer falls down, you can force the guy to
build it up, and this a little bit gets to your point
Michael, up to ארבע אמות. arba amos. So if the wall was
עשר אמות eser amos high and it fell down and I said
I don't want to build again, no, I can force you to
rebuild it, but I can only force you to rebuild it up
to ארבע אמות. arba amos. Okay, but nevertheless I can force you
to build it. So that's very clear, you can force a guy
to build a wall in the yard? Ah, exactly. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, נפל שאני, nafal shani, if it fell it's different.
Now the גמרא Gemara then it was already there, so you're just
asking him to restore it. דמעיקרא מאי קסבר, D'meikara mai kasavar, so
obviously if it fell it's different. What were you even thinking? That
case obviously was a case where it was already there and that's
why you can force it. No, סיפא איצטריכא ליה. seifa itztricha lei.
I need it for the end. מ-ארבע אמות ולמעלה אין מחייבין אותו,
M'arba amos u'lemala ein mechayvin oso, meaning I thought the reason the
משנה mishna gave the case of it already being there was to
tell you a חידוש chiddush that I can't make you build it
up to עשר אמות eser amos even if it started as עשר.
eser. But the basic point that I can force you to build
a wall would be true whether it pre-existed or didn't pre-exist. Like
you understand the משנה mishna says two things: you had a wall
עשר אמות, eser amos, it fell down, I can force you to
build it
ארבע אמות arba amos not עשר אמות. eser amos. So the first
חידוש chiddush is I can't force you to build it עשר אמות,
eser amos, right? But how about the basic point that I can
force you to build it altogether? Okay, is that because it pre-existed
or would that be regardless of whether it pre-existed? So that the
גמרא Gemara said is we thought that would be regardless of whether
it pre-existed and the answer is no, maybe it's only because it
pre-existed. We'll end here but I want to say one last thing
about why is it different when the wall already existed? So I
might think if the wall already existed the reason you can force
me now is a type of a some דיני ממונות dinei mammonos
type of a thing, like there's been an implicit agreement that we
had made before and we have to live up to that previous
agreement from before. But רש"י Rashi says differently. Just look at this
little רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi says
נפל שאני, nafal shani, I don't know where to tell you, it's
like ten lines before the lines get wide. רש"י Rashi says
שכל... no, that wasn't the רש"י Rashi I was thinking about. Maybe
it was תוספות. Tosafos. Yeah, look at תוספות. Tosafos. רש"י says you
have to rebuild it because that was already the agreement to have
a wall, so it's just living up to that contractual agreement. Look
at תוספות, Tosafos, נפל שאני, nafal shani, שהורגלו לעשות דבר הצנעה בחצר
וילמדו זה מזה. she'hurgelu la'asos devar hatzneah b'chatzer v'yilmedu zeh mizeh. Once
we've been living with a wall between us, I have more of
a right to maintain that degree of privacy, so it becomes not
a contractual obligation to build a wall but because now you're looking
at me really is causing me היזק, hezek, really is invading a
privacy that by now I have a right to expect. So it's
interesting about whether I have a right to expect and whether it's
damage might depend on what the pre-existing norms and realities were. So
to be continued tomorrow. Yes, ארבע אמות. arba amos.